Okay, so in this video
then, we're going to
be covering the Schedule Management Plan.
And the Schedule Management
Plan, remember, just
like any other management
plan, is documenting how.
Is documenting how we're going to develop
the schedule?
How we're going to plan, execute, monitor,
and control our schedule
management process.
It's documenting procedures.
It's establishing procedures for planning,
developing, and so on and so forth,
monitoring controlling or anything to do
with the schedule.
Now just as a quick review,
remember the schedule management
plan is a component of the
project management plan.
The project management plan is made up of
three major components.
It's made up of the subsidiary plans.
The subsidiary management
plans is made up of the
baselines and it's made
up of additional components.
The schedule management plan is a
component of one of the subsidiary plans
and or rather the schedule management plan
is a component of the subsidiary plan the
subsidiary management plan okay now the
schedule management plan then does not
contain the schedule just like any
management plan it doesn't contain any
actual results the schedule management
plan contains details on how they're right
it's containing procedures
Such as, for example,
then, how we're going
to develop the schedule?
What methodology are we going to be using?
The methodology that you
need for the purpose of the PMP
exam is critical path methodology,
the critical path method.
And we have separate videos on the
critical path method.
However, what methodology we are using,
that's going to be documented here.
You don't always have to use a critical
path method.
Different industries is
going to use different
methodologies to develop the schedule.
you develop your schedule
differently if you're in a
predictive project versus if
you're in an agile project, right?
They're going to be developed differently.
And one of the reasons
they're developed differently
is because of the units of
measure that we're using.
So the what unit of
measure and tolerance limit,
that's also documented in
the schedule management plan.
So for example, then, we don't always have
to use days, weeks, months, when we're
developing the schedule, right,
or hours, right?
Unit of measure could simply be something
like FTEs, full-time equivalence.
This activity requires 2 and a quarter
full-time equivalence.
Or it could be in terms of level of
effort, such as staff hours.
This activity requires 30 hours worth of
work.
It doesn't necessarily mean that one
person is going to be sitting down
continuously for 30 hours working on this
activity.
No, it just means that, you know, there
may be a couple of people working on it.
Right.
So, you know, some people, you may work a
couple of hours here,
a couple of hours there.
All together, it'll take 30 hours.
You may give them three weeks to perform
the work, four weeks to perform the work,
but overall, it's 30 hours level of
effort.
All right.
So if you were to hire, for example,
a contractor to do the work, and you give
them three weeks, you're not going to pay
them for three weeks.
You're going to pay them for 30 hours.
It's going to change them 30 hours to do
the work.
Okay.
So again, whatever unit of measure you're
going to be using in an agile environment,
you don't use days, weeks, months,
hours.
And in agile environment, it's a level of
effort.
It's more relative estimating,
right?
The level of effort is relative
estimating, right?
So, which, again, we are covering in a
separate video.
So again, whatever unit
of measure we're using is
all documented here in the
Schedule Management Plan.
Also, things like the tolerance limit.
Tolerance limit meaning, do we have any
tolerance for going behind schedule?
Or do we have a fixed deadline?
So, again, that's going to be documented
here.
Sometimes we have a fixed deadline.
Sometimes we absolutely need to finish
this project.
There's no tolerance for going behind
schedule.
Regulatory requirement, for example.
If we don't meet this
deadline, then we might be
in violation of some kind
of regulatory compliance.
right and so there is no tolerance limit
or we may have a tolerance limit if we go
a little bit behind schedule right there
might not be a problem but what happens if
we do start going behind schedule how do
we handle that situation what do we do in
that situation what if senior management
increases the scope of the project and now
increasing that scope of the project is
going to push out our timeline how do we
handle that situation what do we do in
that situation then So again, all of these
procedures are documented here in the
Schedule Management Plan.
Also in Schedule Management, part of
Schedule Management is actually
determining what activities we need to
perform.
So remember the schedule
is determining when
we are going to be performing activities.
In scope management, scope management is
about determining what activities need to
be performed, or rather, what work needs
to be performed, whereas schedule
management is determining when do we need
to perform that work.
So in scope management, we are
decomposing, we are creating the work
breakdown structure, so decomposing our
project down to the work package.
It's in schedule management now where
we're taking each work package and then
further decomposing it, breaking it down
into individual activities.
and then from those activities we can
determine which is the first activity
which is the next which is a third
activity which activities can be run in
parallel right and then how long each
activity is going to take and then how
long is the entire project is going to
take so from there we're going to be
developing our schedule now the schedule
management plan then is an artifact an
important artifact and
it's considered as an
output of the plan schedule
management process.
So when we're looking at the PIMBOC guide
processes in version six, the very first
process in schedule management is plan
schedule management and the output of that
or the artifact that we're
creating, the document
that we're creating is the
schedule management plan.
Now two other important artifacts that you
need to know about are these two here,
the project schedule and the schedule
baseline and these are outputs of a
process called develop schedule right so
develop the schedule so these are outputs
of that process right and develop schedule
then is basically the process where you
know we talk about the critical path
method so the two outputs then is the
project schedule and the schedule baseline
so project schedule as the name suggests
it is a about the critical path,
we're going to start about the start date
and end date, the early start,
late start of each particular activity.
We are developing the schedule for that
activity.
Or rather, we're developing the schedule
for that project.
So that's what the project schedule is.
It's a planned start and end dates.
Right.
So for each activity, so before we can
determine the start and end dates for each
activity, we first have to determine what
those activities are.
And that's where the decomposition comes
in, right, the tool and technique
decomposition, where we're taking the work
package, decomposing
it into individual activities.
And then from those activities,
we're going to sequence those activities.
This is the first activity, this is the
next, then determine how long activities
are going to take, and then come up with
the critical path, do a forward pass,
backward pass, again, separate videos,
which we're going to cover.
Some of those activities are going to be
milestones, right?
A milestone is a significant point on a
project.
It's a key deliverable on a project.
So we're going to be determining what
those milestones are.
A lot of times we might be showing this as
a Gant chart.
So we're going to talk about Gant chart.
Now, you don't need to know a lot about
Gant charts for the PMP exam.
You just need to know that it is there.
There is a tool and is a way of showing
your schedule.
Now, the project
schedule then, as I said, is
your start, your planned
start and end dates.
From there, then, you're going to be
determining the actual results.
Are we head a schedule?
Are we behind schedule?
And so and so forth.
So we're going to be
using this then to track the
performance, a schedule
performance of your project.
Now, the other artifact
here, the other document,
is this one called the schedule baseline.
Now, what's the
difference then between the
project schedule and
the schedule baseline?
Because they both basically sound like
there's the same thing.
Well, the basic difference is,
I mean, there's only, there's just one
word that distinguishes between the
project schedule and the schedule
baseline, and that's this first word here,
approved.
The schedule baseline is the approved
version of the schedule, right?
That's literally all it is.
Remember, what is a baseline?
So, as part of the project management
plan, there are three baselines.
You have the scope baseline, schedule
baseline, cost baseline.
In this case, this one is the Schedule
Baseline.
And any baseline, right, approved by who?
Key stakeholders.
And who are those key stakeholders?
Well, the project manager, as well as the
sponsor, as well as other key stakeholders
that make up the project leadership team,
as well as some, any key team members.
Collectively, everyone needs all of those
appropriate.
players, they need to agree, approve,
sign off.
In this case, on the schedule,
and now the schedule has been baseline.
One of the key things about the baseline
then is actual results are going to be
compared against the
baseline, and any changes
now need to go through a change control.
So in this case, then, we are talking
about a predictive life cycle.
So in a predictive life cycle, That's
where we have the change control board.
So any changes then to the baseline now
need to go through a change control.
So these are a couple of important
artifacts then in schedule.
So we have the schedule management plan.
So that is an output of plan schedule
management.
Then you have the project schedule and the
schedule baseline.
Both of these then are outputs of develop
schedule.